בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"ד, samech daled, 64.
We are on ס"ג ע"ב, samech gimmel amud bet, a little behind.
We are in the middle of a discussion about swearing by and
mentioning the names of foreign gods. We mentioned some of the practical
aspects about that
and the whole תוספות Tosfos there that we did at the end
of yesterday that also gets onto core questions of how הלכה halakha
treats Christianity.
And now we pick up with three lines before the lines get
wide. כי
אתא עולא בת בקלנבו Ki ata Ulla bat be-Kalanbo
when עולא Ulla came, he slept in this place called קלנבו Kalanbo
and apparently that was the name of some foreign god. Okay, there
are some cities in the US that have the name of you
know certain names. Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
אמר ליה רבא והיכא בת מר, amar lei Rava ve-heicha bat mar,
how did you sleep there? Because you're not supposed to, like it
says, you're not supposed to even say to somebody wait for me
by this עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. How did you sleep in that
town? Now I don't know, did he maybe he didn't say the
name of the town, maybe just slept there, but anyway apparently he
said the name of the town. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, והיכא בת מר, ve-heicha bat mar, where did
you sleep? I'm sorry, not how did you sleep there, where did
you sleep? אמר ליה בקלנבו Amar lei be-Kalanbo in this town. אמר
ליה והא כתיב, Amar lei ve-ha k'siv, ha, gotcha, ושם אלהים אחרים
לא תזכירו. ve-shem elohim acherim lo tazkiru. Oh no,
anyway so the problem wasn't that he slept there, the problem was
that he said the name. Wait, you're not supposed to say the
name of a foreign god. אמר ליה הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
lei hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, this is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says, כל עבודת כוכבים דכתיבה בתורה מותר להזכיר שמה. kol avodat kochavim
de-ksiva be-Torah mutar lehazkir shemah. If God's already gonna say the name,
we're allowed to say the name. So if it's mentioned in the
תורה, Torah, you're allowed to say the name.
Not to take an oath in that name or whatever, God forbid,
but to mention. והא היכא כתיבא? Ve-ha heicha k'siva? Where is this
written? דכתיב, De-ksiv, so תורה Torah is writ large here to include
תנ"ך, Tanakh, okay? Because it
says כרע בל קרס נבו. kara Bel kares Nevo. So bowed down
בל Bel was the name of like some foreign god, קרס, kares,
so that's like what was the name of his town here? קלנבו.
Kalanbo. So קרס kares like crouched down or something נבו. Nevo. So
somehow the word נבו Nevo there, קלנבו, Kalanbo, קל נבו, Kal Nevo,
so you have so the נבו Nevo was presumably the name of
the foreign god. So that's mentioned. ואי לא כתיבא לא? Ve-i lo
k'siva lo? But are you telling me if it's not written you're
not allowed to say that? מתני רב מששרשיה ראה אחת מרובה כשלש
שהיא כמגידון לשילה. Masni Rav Mesharshaya ra achas meruba ke-shalosh she-hi ke-Migiddon
le-Shilo. If somebody a זב, zav, somebody with a penile emission, whatever
that would make him טמא, tamei, not semen. Anyway, so if you
see three separate you know emissions, the person has a full level
of טומאה. tumah. Let's say it's one level of emission but it's
enough that it could be three, like you know it goes on
for a long enough time. So how much is that long enough
time? So one large amount which is equal to three, שהיא she-hi
it's the amount of time that it takes to walk from מגידון
Migiddon to שילה, Shilo, שהן she-hein which is שתי טבילות ושני סיפוגים.
shte tevilot ve-shne sipugim.
So we have to imagine the amount of time to have had
an emission, go to the מקוה, mikvah, dry yourself off, have another
emission, go to the מקוה, mikvah, dry yourself off, have another emission.
Because you know the what breaks it up into three is the
ability to have gone to the מקוה mikvah between. Anyway, that's not
relevant for us. What's relevant is it mentions the amount of time
it takes to go from this place called מגידון. Migiddon. And מגידון
Migiddon from גד, Gad, not G-O-D, גימל דלת, gimmel dalet, is the
name of some idolatrous god. So it says ha so where so
that's mentioned in the משנה. Mishna. Where is it mentioned in תנ"ך?
Tanakh? So the גמרא Gemara says הרי זה זב גמורה, harei zeh
zav gemura, anyway that's the end of the teaching, that's a זב.
zav. אמר רבינא גד נמי כתיב. Amar Ravina Gad nami k'siv. No
that word also appears in תנ"ך Tanakh as the name of an
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. דכתיב העורכים לגד שלחן. De-ksiv ha-orkhim le-Gad shulchan.
It's actually quite explicit. Those that prepare a table for גד, Gad,
for this idol.
Okay so that was a type of a form of worship. No
we gotta move on.
אמר רב נחמן.
Amar
Rav Nachman.
Monday, Tuesday, January and February.
Right, except that you're not
actually saying Thor's day or you know or Woden's day, you're saying
Wednesday. But it might be a bigger problem if it were, but
I think the general assumption is that if they're dead gods it's
not a problem. Gods that nobody is still worshipping. Of course if
you like the novel American Gods, then we could have a whole
discussion. Okay, anyway.
In that time they were still worshipping קלנבו Kalanbo or whatever it
was?
Oh, but that was okay because it was in the תורה. Torah.
You're asking about ones that weren't in the תורה. Torah.
But okay fine, either way could have been an answer then right?
Either they weren't worshipping.
Right, the general assumption is that if nobody's worshipping the god it's
not a problem anymore.
Even
for months or of
gods.
That is true too, that's true right? The names of the months
we got from בבל Bavel and they're the name of Babylonian gods
or some. If they were worshipping at that time. Right, yeah, that's
a good question. I don't know. Yeah. That's a very good question.
Yeah. I mean that look, I don't know how is you know
that's what I said before. It's like it's one thing to say
not to use them in an oath, but not to just say
them in passing, even not with reverence but just in passing, which
is the context we're talking about here, which seems that it would
make conversation pretty difficult when a language is sort of suffused with
it.
It especially be you know like especially you go on you're traveling
they might be Saint Square.
Well Saint as we said yesterday isn't a god. Okay. אמר רב
נחמן כל ליצנותא, Amar Rav Nachman kol litznuta, but there's other places
like the one that's corpus whatever. Okay. אמר אמר. Amar amar. אמר
רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, כל ליצנותא אסורא חוץ מליצנותא דעבודת כוכבים.
kol leitzanuta asura chutz mi-leitzanuta de-avodat kochavim. You're not allowed to speak
in a mocking, like, you know, mockery, that doesn't breed a good
sort of attitude, you know, towards the world and people or whatever,
so you're not allowed to be mocking with the exception of עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. Okay, דשריא, desharya, it's permissible. דכתיב, dichtiv, כרע בל
קרס נבו, kara Bel kares Nevo, crouched down Bel, you know, sort
of bowed down Nevo, קרסו כרעו יחדיו, kirsu karu yachdav, they have
basically crouched down, you know, together, לא יכלו מלט משא, lo yachlu
malet massa, they could not escape the burden. So basically it means
they couldn't escape the burden of their, of, you know, their food
and they basically had to crouch down and defecate. So it's basically
describing these idolatrous gods whatever, you know, defecating, okay, because they can't
handle their food. So anyway, it's a way of, I mean you
already find this in the נביאים, Nevi'im, you know, it's a way
of counteracting the influence is you just make a mockery of it.
Eliyahu does that.
Right, exactly. Okay. וכתיב, u-chsiv, דברו לעגלות, dibru la-aglot, speak to the
עגלות, aglot, the עגלי זהב eglei zahav that they had, you know,
in the Israelite kingdom, בית און Beit Aven of the city of
sin, which is really of בית אל. Beit El. Okay, but it's
obviously a play here on words, יגורו שכן שמרון, yaguru shochen shamron,
will fear those who dwell in Shamron, כי אבל עליו עמו ki
avel alav amo because the nation, the, these calves, the golden calves
will be taken, you know, when whoever it was, Sancheirev came and
exiled them. Okay, because the people will mourn for it, כי אבל
עליו עמו, ki avel alav amo, where am I, I lost my
place, וכמריו עליו יגילו, u-chmarav alav yagilu,
but the priests, they will rejoice. Why will they rejoice that their
god is taken? על כבודו כי גלה ממנו al kvodo ki gala
mimenu for the honor of this god that was, that went into
exile from me. So what does that mean? Says, אל תקרי כבודו,
al tikrei kvodo, its honor, אלא כבידו, ela kveido, the weight, they
had to deal with the weight of all of the defecation of
these calves and now they'll be sort of free of it. So
that is again a similar... Whoa, I'm sorry, that's an Amber Alert.
Okay. All right.
Okay. All right. So it says, okay, so it says like this.
אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chsiv, what's meant,
ועתה יוסיפו לחטוא ויעשו להם מסכה מכספם כתבונם, ve-ata yosifu lachato vayaasu
lahem massecha mikaspam kithvunam,
now they have increased in their sin and they made for themselves
a molten image
from their silver like their
image, עצבים. atzabim. What's עצבים? atzabim? Like their idols I guess, yeah.
Anyway, their idols. Okay, מאי כתבונם עצבים? mai kithvunam atzabim? What does
it mean like their idols were like their images? מלמד שכל אחד
ואחד עשה דמות יראתו, melamed she-kol echad ve-echad asa dmut yirato, every
individual had their own little idol, their own little personal idol, ומניחה
בכיסו u-manicha ve-kiso
and kept it in their like in their pouch, בשעה
שזוכרן, be-sha'ah she-zochran, any time that they had, that they remembered their
god, מוציאו מתוך חיקו, motzio mi-toch chiko,
they took it out of their like of their, you know, literally
of their chest, they took it out of their pouch, ומחבקו ומנשקו,
u-mchabko u-mnashko,
they kissed it. Okay, so it became a little talisman is the
point, okay. Like this is god that you worship, anything oh you
have a little memory you you kiss your little thing. Okay, so
okay. מאי זובחי אדם עגלים ישקון, mai zovechei adam agalim yishakun,
what is meant by the verse,
what were we trying to do with that verse just before?
Just because? Yeah, where in this context, and it's a way of
mocking. It's not the mocking like oh they're going in there defecating
everywhere, but it's a mocking like oh they treated like this little,
you know, talisman they kiss it every time they remember it. Okay,
so okay. מאי זובחי אדם עגלים ישקון, mai zovechei adam agalim yishakun,
so
literally it means those that slaughter people will kiss the calves. What
does that mean? אמר רבי יצחק דבי רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
de-vei Rabbi Ammi, so it's from the פסוקים psukim from the same
area here in הושע. Hoshea. So he said in the name of
Rabbi Ammi: שהיו משרתי עבודה זרה נותנים עיניהם בבעלי ממון, she-hayu meshartai
avodah zarah nosnim eineihem be-baalei mammon,
the attendants to the idols would, and these were that they worshipped
these calves, the calves were sort of their objects of worship. So
what they would do is they want they put their eyes on
people that were very wealthy, they would like, you know, they wanted
to sort of get their wealth to their to their temple. So
what they would do is
ומרעיבים את העגלים, u-mar'ivim et ha-agalim, they would starve the calves, which
were the things that were being worshipped, ועושים דמות עצבים, ve-osim dmut
atzabim, they made images of the people whom they were, you know,
whom they wanted to sort of, you know, the wealthy people, they
put it in front of the calves. So the calves were very,
very hungry and they had the images of these people in front
of them, ומעמידם בצד אבוסיהם, u-ma'amidam be-tzad avuseihem,
and they put them right by the troughs of the calves, ומוציאים
אותם לחוץ. u-motzi'im otam la-chutz.
So then they took these starving calves out of their, you know,
pen, and these people were among the worshippers and the calves had
all they had seen was their images. So what did they do?
So כיון שראם, keivan she-ro'am, they saw these wealthy people, רצו אחריהן
וממשמשים בהן, ratzu achareihen u-m'mishmshim bahen, they'd run after them, they'd rub
up against them, maybe they thought finally they would give them some
food or something, אומרים לו, omrim lo,
so the priest said, oh look, עבודה זרה חפץ בך, avodah zarah
chafetz be-cha, our god desires you, they're rubbing up... against you. What
they want is they want you to offer yourself up as a
sacrifice to them. Okay, so יבא ויזבח עצמו yavo v'yizbach atzmo go
slaughter yourself.
Now I don't know how that helped the coffers of the temple
unless they said that part of the deal was that the temple
will inherit your wealth. Anyway, so that's זובחי אדם, zovchei adam, they
slaughtered the people to the calves. Okay, now where's the עגלים ישקון?
agalim yishakun? Where's the kissing of the calves? So where was it?
ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, hai זובחי אדם עגלים ישקון, zovchei adam agalim
yishakun, עגלים ישקון לזבוח אדם. agalim yishakun lizboach adam. So
apparently the means that afterwards they would kiss the calves for doing
a good job. Anyway, so Rava said that's wrong, then it shouldn't
be those that slaughter the calves, slaughtering of the people will kiss
the calves, it should be they'll kiss the calves in order to
slaughter the people. I don't exactly get what the question is, but
anyway, they first kiss them for the purpose of, okay, what does
Rashi say? ישקון לזבוח אדם, yishakun lizboach adam, ישקון לזבוח אדם מיבעי
ליה, yishakun lizboach adam mibayei lei, להם הם הקומיים ומהעגלות הללו נושקים
אתכם. lahem hem hakomayim u'meha'agalot halalu noshkim etchem. Oh,
I see. No, it wasn't that the priest would kiss the calves.
The calves would go up and rub up and kiss the people.
Okay, so it should be the order should have been different. It
should have been ישקון, yishakun, those that they kiss, לזבוח אדם, lizboach
adam, they kiss them in order to slaughter the people. Whatever. Anyway,
אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, כל הזובח את בנו לעבודת כוכבים,
kol hazoveach et bno l'avodat kochavim, no
this is what the verse means. Anybody who would slaughter their son
to the god, to the gods, אמר לו, amar lo,
so the priest should say, oh my, דורון גדול הקריב לו, doron
gadol hikriv lo, you brought a great offering to our god. יבוא
ויישק לו, yavo v'yishak lo, you know, come and kiss the god,
or I don't know if that means or let the god come
and kiss you. Anyway, so that's זובחי אדם, zovchei adam, the people
who slaughter humans, who slaughter their children to the gods, so עגלים
ישקון, agalim yishakun, they're entitled to go and kiss the gods. Okay,
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, ואנשי בבל
עשו את סכות בנות. v'anshei Bavel asu et Succoth Benot. סכות בנות.
Succoth Benot. So מאי ניהו? mai nihu?
So this is a list in a פסוק pasuk in מלכים Melachim
of all the different types of idols that were made from different,
these different people. So they made Succoth Benot, what does that refer
to? תרנגולת. tarnegolet. So that's a hen. That was their god. ואנשי
כות עשו את נרגל. v'anshei Chut asu et Nergal. So what's Nergal?
ומאי ניהו? u'mai nihu? תרנגול. tarnegol. That was, that's a rooster. I
have no idea. I have no idea. ואנשי חמת עשו את אשימא.
v'anshei Chamat asu et Ashima. ומאי ניהו? u'mai nihu?
So what's that? ברחא קרחא. barcha karcha. So that is what does
Rashi say? That is, oh yes, a goat, okay, and it's called
a bald goat because it doesn't have wool. והעוים עשו נבחן ואת
תרתק. v'ha'Avim asu Nivchan v'et Tartak.
What's that Tartak? ומאי ניהו? u'mai nihu? כלב וחמור. kelev v'chamor. So
they had their for their god a dog and a donkey. So
dog from the word נבח nivach is like to bark. I don't
know how Tartak means a donkey. והספרוים שורפים את בניהם באש. v'haSepharvim
sorfim et bneihem ba'esh.
That's where we were going because we mentioned child sacrifice and it's
also going to tie into the next משנה mishna which speaks about
serving מולך. Molech. So they would burn their sons in the fire
לאדרמלך וענמלך, l'Adrammelech v'Anammelech, אלוהי ספרוים, elohei Sepharvim,
to those two gods of the Sepharvim. ומאי ניהו? u'mai nihu?
So what are they? הפרד והסוס. ha'pered v'hasus. That would be the
mule and the horse. אדרמלך, Adrammelech, דאדר ליה למריה בטעוניה, d'adar lei
l'marei b'tiunei, that it sort of it honors its master, the king,
whatever its master, by taking a burden, so that's why it's a
mule. וענמלך, v'Anammelech, דעני ליה למריה בקרבא, d'ani lei l'marei b'karva,
that it responds back to its master like in war, like it,
you know, it answers its master, it follows its master even into
war. Okay, anyway, אף חזקיה מלך יהודה, af Chizkiyahu melech Yehuda, so
ביקש לעשות לו כן, bikesh la'asot lo ken,
even Chizkiyahu they wanted to actually offer as a, his father wanted
to bring him as a child offering to this god. Rashi says
we know this because it says באחז, b'Achaz, who was Chizkiyahu's father,
גם את בנו העביר באש, gam et bno he'evir ba'esh,
that he passed his son through the fire as an idolatrous act.
And Rashi says the only son we know about is Chizkiyahu. So
presumably they were trying to actually burn Chizkiyahu as a offering to
this god. Okay, ביקש לעשות כן, bikesh la'asot ken, אלא שסכתו אמו
סלמנדרא, ela she'sechato imo salamandra, but his mother had had this is
sort of like
the Achilles story, his mother had like anointed him with the oil
of a salamander which protected him from the fire. Okay, it's supposed
to have magical qualities.
Which must be born from the fire.
Right. Oh, is that why? Oh, good point.
It says it emerged from an oven in which a fire is
burned for seven years.
Okay, got it. Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, יודעין היו ישראל בעבודת כוכבים שאין
בה ממש. yodin hayu Yisrael b'avodat kochavim she'ein bah mamash. Now we've
listed all these עבודות זרות, avodot zarot, and after all you now
know their names, the ones that are in the תנ"ך Tanakh you're
allowed to say. And anyway we had a good laugh at them
and we were mocking them. Now we're going to go back and
sort of deal with this issue, if they're such a mockery, right,
why were we, why did we stray after them? Okay, so
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, יודעין היו
ישראל בעבודת כוכבים שאין בה
ממש. yodin hayu Yisrael b'avodat kochavim she'ein bah mamash. Israel always knew,
they always knew that they were meaningless. ולא עבדו עבודת כוכבים אלא
להתיר להם עריות בפרהסיא. v'lo avdu avodat kochavim ela l'hatir lahem arayot
b'farhesya.
They only served idolatry to allow them to engage in illicit relationships
in public. Only reason they worshipped idols was because it would have
freed them from the constraints of the מצוות, Mitzvot, because you know
they would have said we're no longer, you know, keeping God's תורה,
Torah, we're following the idols. And in particular it was the drive
for sexual freedom that led them astray, okay, and that led them
to sort of, now it might be specifically that some of these
pagan worships involved, you know, sort of type of sexual acts and
so on, but even without that it means that the תורה Torah
is very demanding in terms of sexual restraint, right, and they wanted
greater freedom. So you know that's always the question, right, when somebody
leaves are they leaving because of theological issues or are they leaving
because you know there's a famous story that one of the,
I forget who it was, I think anyway this big like משכיל,
maskil, you know, said I you know I'm leaving all this it
doesn't make any make any sense anymore and he had all these
questions and I heard this in the name of the הגר"א, Hagra,
I don't know, anyway so the students of the הגר"א Hagra heard
this and he said, you know, רבי, Rebbe, you have to talk
to this guy and give him answers. So he talked to the
guy and he said here are all my questions, whatever. He says
no I'm sorry I can't help you. So the guy walked away.
So the students said רבי, Rebbe, I don't understand you know everything
how come you couldn't answer his questions? He said those weren't questions,
they were answers.
So, you know, so what? Yeah, it's very complicated, right? How much
is it exactly, how much is it because you want to be
free and that's why you have all your questions and how much
is it really because you have your questions? So anyway, so that's
what this is saying. It was not because the attraction to the
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, they wanted to be free of the restraints.
Okay, so שאין בו ממש
ולא עבדו עבודה זרה אלא להתיר להם עריות בפרהסיא. she'ein bo mamash
v'lo avdu avodah zarah ela lehatir lahem arayot befarhesya. מתיב רב משארשיא!
Metiv Rav Mesharshya! רב משארשיא Rav Mesharshya asked, what do you mean?
I'm going to quote you all these פסוקים psukim where it seems
that they were very seriously passionate about their עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay, here's one. כי זכור בניהם מזבחותם. Ki zachor benehem mizbechotam. So
it says they would remember their you know their gods like remembering
their sons, okay? דאמר רבי אלעזר כאדם שיש לו געגועין על בנו.
D'amar Rabbi Elazar k'adam sheyesh lo ga'aguim al bno. Like you know
when you remember your son who's far away and your heart you're
in that's what it was like for them when they would think
of their gods. So that's that's a real passion for them, a
real connection. So בתר דאדבקו ביה, Batar d'idabku beih, no, that's after
they started running after them. The initial, you know, the initial motivation
was to be free of the constraints, right? But once we spent
a lot of time being עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah, we
started to really have a deeper connection. תא שמע, Ta shma, come
in here. ונתתי פגריכם על פגרי גלוליכם. Venatati pigrechem al pigrei giluleichem.
I will give put your corpses on the corpses of your, you
know, idols there. The תורה Torah itself is already mocking it, right?
referring to the idols as like your defecations or whatever. Anyway, אמר
אליהו הצדיק אמר. Amar Eliyahu HaTzaddik amar. So it said אמרו, amru,
they
said אליהו הצדיק היה מחזר על תפוחי רעב שבירושלים. Eliyahu HaTzaddik haya
mechazer al tapuchei ra'av shebiYerushalayim. אליהו הצדיק, Eliyahu HaTzaddik,
what can I tell you, it's a good point, anyway was going
around all those that had been bloated by famine in Jerusalem. פעם
אחת מצא תינוק שהיה תפוח ומוטל באשפה. Pa'am achat matza tinok shehaya
tapuach umutal ba'ashpah.
He found an infant, a small, he must have seen an infant
anyway, a small child who was bloated and there in the, in
the dung heap. אמר לו מאיזו משפחה אתה? Amar lo me'eizo mishpacha
ata?
Where do you come from? אמר לו ממשפחה פלונית Amar lo mimishpacha
plonit such and such a
family אני. ani. אמר לו כלום נשתייר מאותה משפחה? Amar lo klum
nishtayer me'otah mishpacha? Is anything left of that family because they all
now were dying presumably due to the sin of idolatry.
אמר לו לאו, Amar lo lav, no, חוץ ממני, chutz mimeni, I'm
the one remnant of this large family. אמר לו אם אני מלמדך
דבר שאתה חי בו אתה למד? Amar lo im ani melamedcha davar
she'ata chai bo ata lamed? If I will teach you something that
will give you life, are you prepared to learn it? אמר לו
הן, Amar lo hen, yes. אמר לו, Amar lo, he says here
it is, here's the secret.
אמר בכל יום שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד. Amar bechol yom
Shma Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad. Accept God as your God, reject
your idol worship, that will give you life. אמר לו, Amar lo,
he said to him,
חס שלא להזכיר בשם השם. Chas shelo lehazkir beshem Hashem. God forbid
that I should say God's name, okay? This is actually quoting a
פסוק. pasuk. There's a פסוק pasuk that says that they'll say חס
להזכיר בשם השם. Chas lehazkir beshem Hashem. שלא לימדו אבי ואמי. Shelo
limdu avi v'imi. My mother and father never taught me that. God
forbid that I should accept your, you know, your God. מיד הוציא
יראתו. Miyad hotzi yirato. He took his little idol out of his,
out of like his cloak מחקו ומחבקו ומנשקו. mechako umichabko umenashko. He
hugged it and he kissed it עד שנבקעה כריסו. ad shenivke'ah kriso.
His stomach exploded ונפלה יראתו לארץ. venafelah yirato la'aretz. His God, his
idol fell onto the earth ונפל הוא עליה venafal hu aleha and
he fell on top of it לקיים מה שנאמר ונתתי פגריכם על
פגרי גלוליכם. lekayem mah shene'emar venatati pigrechem al pigrei giluleichem.
I will put your corpse on tops of the corpse of your
idols and also like your, your dung because his whole stomach exploded.
Anyway so look, they so were attached to it that they were
willing to give up their lives for it. How could you say
they just did it to permit themselves sexual sins? בתר דאדבקו ביה.
Batar d'idabku beih. That's after they began to cleave to it. That's
heavy. That answers, after they began to cleave to it, which is
actually a very true thing. There are things that initially motivate you
and then it's too late because then you're already committed to this
whole way of life and you internalize it.
ירבעם Yerovam changed it in order to, you know, divide the kingdom.
Well right, that's true, there was a lot of other reasons as
well. Exactly, political reasons right. תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here.
Come, come here. Now this is going to be a very famous
מדרש, Midrash, very, very famous. ויזעקו בקול גדול, Vayiz'aku bekol gadol, this
is about the, in the time of נחמיה, Nechemya, the leaders of
the people when they returned for the בית שני. Bayit Sheni. They
called out in a great voice אל השם אלוהיהם, el Hashem Elokeihem,
to Hashem their God. מאי אמרו, Mai amru, or what did they
say? אמר רב יהודה ואיתימא רב יונתן, Amar Rav Yehuda ve'iteima Rav
Yonatan, בייא בייא, Baya Baya, woe, woe, woe, they were saying, the
leaders at this time. היינו דאחריבה לביתא, Hayinu de'achriva lebeita, they were
talking about the desire, the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for עבודה זרה,
Avoda Zara, the passion for idolatry. This is the thing that destroyed
our temple, דקליה להיכלא, dekalyah leheichala, it burnt the, you know, the
sanctuary, וקטלינהו לצדיקי, vekatlinhu letzadikay,
it caused the righteous to be murdered, ואגלינהו לישראל מארעהון, ve'aglinhu leYisrael
me'arhon,
it caused Israel to be exiled from their land, ועדיין הוא מרקד
ביננא, ve'adayin hu meraked beinan, it's still dancing among us. Here we
are, we've returned for the second בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and people
are still desiring to run after עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. כלום יהבתיה
לן אלא לקבולי ביה אגרא, Clum yahvteya lan ela lekabuli bei agra,
the only reason God gave us this desire, this passion for עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara was that we should receive reward if we were
able to conquer over it. You know what? לא איהו בעינן ולא
אגרא בעינן, Lo ihu beinan velo agra beinan, we don't want it
and we don't want its reward. We're better to do without it.
Okay. So anyway, so you see how, so look, you see how
internalized this was even when they were trying now to return and
everything, they still couldn't get rid of this passion for עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. בתר דאביק בהו טפי, Batar de'avik behu tfei, fine.
That's what happened after many centuries of running after it, they totally
internalized it. But that wasn't the initial motivation. Now that we're okay,
so now we're done with this whole discussion of whether they were
motivated because of the desire for עבודה זרה Avoda Zara per se
or for the desire for sexual freedom and then they internalized the
desire for עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. But now we're going to continue
this famous אגדתא Agadata about in the time of the בית שני
Bayit Sheni the leaders, the אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah here,
wanted to do away with the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. So here's what they did.
יתבי תלתא יומא בתעניתא, Yatvei tlata yoma betanita, they set three days
of a fasting. בעו רחמי, Bau rachamei, pray to God to be
free of the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
נפלה פיתקא מרקיעא, Nafla pitka merkia,
a little, a little like a writ, like a little piece of
paper, what? A note, thank you, a little note fell from heaven,
what? A little note fell from heaven like we normally put the
little פיתקאs pitka in the, in the כותל. Kotel. Here it's coming
the other direction, okay?
So a little note fell from heaven, דכתיב בה אמת, dechativ bah
emet, truth. Like, like being basically like I'm signing off on your
request, you know, fine, I'll give you the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara
for עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. אמר רב חנינא שמע מינה, Amar Rav
Chanina shma mina, we hear from here again something we say elsewhere,
חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת, chotamo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu emet,
God signs, God's signature is truth, okay? Because God represents ultimate truth.
נפיק כגוריא דנורא, Nafik kegurya denura, so God acceded to their request.
So the, so a like, a little like a lion whelp of
fire, that like a little fire that looked like a little lion
came out מבית קדשי הקדשים, mibeit kadshei hakadashim, from the Holy of
Holies. אמר להו נביא לישראל, Amar lehu navi leYisrael, so the נביא
navi said to them at that time, היינו יצרא דעבודה זרה. Hainu
yitzra de'avoda zara. Ah, that's what you were asking to have dominion
over, that's the יצר עבודה זרה. Yetzer Avoda Zara. Now of course
it's quite shocking that the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara comes from the Holy of Holies. I think to some
degree it's dealing with the problem, you know, that the whole בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash in itself is basically to give a physical, you
know, present way of representing God's presence, you know. So you could
say it sort of raises certain theological challenges. It's not actual a
physical representation of God, but part of the whole attraction of עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara is is that it gives you something very physical
and concrete to relate to. It's very hard to relate to a
non- God that can't be imaged, that can't be seen, you know,
even imagined in concrete human terms. So the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
is some type of a concession of that. And let's not forget
that the כרובים Cherubim were in the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right?
So again, the כרובים Cherubim are what, the chariot of God or
something, but anyway those are all like concessions. So I think it's
very significant that the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara is emerging from the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
It's also a lion cub, right? So it's not at its full
strength, but if you let it grow it will over...
Right, exactly, right, right. Maybe that's true too.
The king, right,
it will over you, right. Or maybe that's the point before, once
we started running after it, it got stronger, yeah, yeah.
And maybe to emphasize how skinny is the line between יצר הרע
Yetzer Hara
and קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right.
You might walk around and be like, oh we're religious, look at
us, right.
But it's actually... Right, right, right.
It's this thin line that distinguishes it. Right. Okay. So
אמר להו נביא לישראל היינו יצרא דעבודה זרה. amar lehu navi leYisrael
hainu yitzra de'avoda zara. בהדי דתפסוהו, Bahadi detafsuhu, so they grabbed it.
I don't know how they grabbed it. It's like a wise, you
know, like how anyway, but anyway, אישתמיט ביניתא מיניה, ishtamit binita minei,
a hair fell out of its head, the יצר, yetzer, this embodied
יצר הרע. Yetzer Hara. ואזל קליה בארבע מאה
פרסי, ve'azal kalia be'arba mea parsei, and the sound that it that
it either the hair dropping or that that it gave off when
its hair fell, you know, was heard for four hundred parasangs, okay?
So now they were very concerned because they saw that when they're
trying to capture the יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, he's going to make
a lot of ruckus. So אמרו היכי נעביד, amru heichi na'avid, what
can we do? דילמא משמיא dilma mishmaya They'll hear up in heaven
that we're capturing him, of course that was the right we were
given from heaven, but maybe there'll be a reversal, maybe they'll have
compassion on him, okay? So אמרי נביא amrei navi so the נביא
navi said שדיוה בדודא דאברא, shadyuhu beduda de'avra, go put him in
a lead cauldron, וכסיוה באברא v'chasiyuha b'avra and seal it with like
lead,
דשאיף קליה dishayif kalei and that'll absorb his sound.
דכתיב dichtiv it says ויאמר זאת הרשעה וישלך אותה אל תוך האיפה,
vayomer zot ha-risha vayashlech otah el toch ha-eifah, this is the wicked
one, throw it into the like cauldron, וישלך את אבן העופרת אל
פיה vayashlech et even ha-oferet el pihah and they put the leaden
stone on its mouth. Okay, אמרי amrei now they said, good, now
we've done it, we've sort of subdued the יצר הרע דעבודה זרה.
Yetzer Hara d'Avoda Zara. They didn't kill it, it's just subdued, you
know it's like its voice is muffled, by the way that's an
important idea, right? It's like maybe we still have a little bit
of that but it's in a muffled way. Okay, but anyway, now
they said הא דעת רצון הוא ha d'et ratzon hu now that
God is acceding to our requests, נבעי רחמי אמיצרא דעבירה, nib'ei rachmei
ayitzra d'aveira, let's pray for the, let's pray have a similar ask
God to give us over the desire for עבירה, aveira, now עבירה
aveira is to sin but often עבירה aveira without being specific means
sexual, okay? So the sexual desire, let's have control over that. Anyone?
For the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara in general?
No, you'll see it very much means sexual, but רחמי rachmei it's
often when the גמרא Gemara says עבירה aveira it means sexual sin.
Okay, בעו רחמי ba'u rachmei they prayed to God, אמסרה בידייהו, imsra
b'yadeihu, God said fine, go ahead, now you have control over the
sexual desire. חבשוה תלתא יומי, chavshuha tlata yomei, they locked it up
for three days. איבעו ביעתא בת יומא לחולה ib'u beita bat yoma
l'chola and then they wanted to find some fresh egg for a
sick person, ולא אשתכח, v'lo ishtakach, no eggs to be found. The
hens weren't laying eggs, right, all things that were related to sex
had sort of been turned off. So אמרו היכי נעביד, amru heichi
na'avid, now okay, what should we do? נבעי פלגא, nib'ei palga, let's
say God just give us like remove the desire for sexual sin,
let's have sort of still healthy sexuality, you know, but for sexual
sin just remove that desire. So פלגא מרקיעא לא יהבי, palga me-reki'a
lo yahavi, no, won't give it halfway. You gotta, if you want
that power you gotta deal with all aspects of that power. Okay,
so כחלינהו לעיניה, kachlinhu l'einei, so what do they do? So כחלינהו
לעיניה, kachlinhu l'einei, they sort of like they poked out its eyes.
כחלינהו kachlinhu literally means they put some like some makeup in its
eyes, they put something in its eyes. Okay, they blind, not blind
it or they blurred its vision. Yeah, I know, I know, yeah
I know, I know, I don't know how that works but somehow
it means, I don't know, how do they translate it? They blinded
its eyes? Yeah, from the context it sounds like that. Anyway, or
they blurred its eyes. Okay, כחלינהו לעיניה, kachlinhu l'einei, אהני בה, ahani
bei, so that meant so God wasn't going to give them half,
but they managed to do a little thing, they couldn't keep it
locked up, they had to let it free, but they injured it
a little on letting it out while they were letting it out.
So anyway, what was the effect of this? דלא איגרי איניש בקרובתיה,
d'lo igrei inish bikrovatei, it helped to deal with the lust, the
desire for incest. Okay, so there's still a desire to sin sexually
with some, with somebody who is not your spouse, or רש"י Rashi
says or when the woman is a נדה, niddah, so that יצר
הרע Yetzer Hara still exists, but the incest יצר הרע Yetzer Hara
has been tamed a little bit. Not totally, but it's been tamed.
Okay. Anyway, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav.
So that was the end of that, that's a very very famous
אגדתא agadata about the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, alright? And we're not done with it, we'll discuss it also
in a later פרק perek as well. According to this, it was
something that we only internalized after we had run after it for
sexual freedom. Notice in both stories the intertwining of sexual drive and
the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, right, exists
in both stories. They worshiped the עבודה זרה Avoda Zara to give
them sexual freedom, right? They got power over the יצר הרע Yetzer
Hara of עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, they wanted power over the you
know the drive for sexual freedom and so on. Okay, but anyway,
according to this, the second story where like you know they had
to free it from the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim or whatever, sounds
like there was a real deep human thing that was motivating them
towards עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. The first part of it, however, was
that it was really just for the sexual freedom and then they
had internalized that יצר הרע. Yetzer Hara. Okay, so now we continue.
Okay, so it says like this, back to general discussions of עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב, Rav,
מעשה בנכרית אחת שהיתה חולה ביותר, ma'aseh b'nochrit achat she-hayta chola beyoter,
there's a story about a certain non-Jewish woman that was very ill,
she was about to die, אמרה אם תעמוד ההיא אשה מחליה, amra
im ta'amod hahi isha me-cholya, if this woman gets up from her
illness, תלך ותעבוד לכל עבודה זרה שבעולם, telech v'ta'avod l'chol avoda zara
she-ba'olam, I will go and I will worship every single god in
the world to say thank you because who knows which god saved
me I guess. You know this is sort of like Pascal's Wager,
right? Do a little Pascal's Wager? No, he basically said like oh
well you don't know if you should believe or not. Well, better
to believe because that way you know you're covering your bases. So,
you know, if you're wrong you didn't lose and if you're right
you got saved. Okay, so anyway she basically said whichever god is
going to save me I'll go thank all of them afterwards, I'll
worship every single god. Okay. So, כיון שהגיעה keivan she-higi'a she came
to the פעור, Peor, שאלה לכומרים sha'ala lakomrim she asked the priests,
sorry did I skip הלכה לכל עבודה זרה שבעולם halcha l'chol avoda
zara shebaolam so she she went she got better. Okay. הלכה לכל
עבודה זרה שבעולם Halcha l'chol avoda zara shebaolam she went to every
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, כיוון שהגיעה לפעור keivan shehigia l'Peor when she
came to the פעור, Peor, שאלה לכומרים sha'ala lakomrim she asked the
priests, במה עובדין לזו? b'meh ovdin l'zo? How do you worship this?
אמרו לה amru lah they said to her, אוכלין תרדין ochlin tardin
you eat beets, ושותין שיכר v'shotin shechar and you drink beer, a
mead, and that makes you very like you know gets the stuff
to pass out of your system, ומטריזין בפניה u'matrizin b'faneha and you
defecate,
actually מטריזין matrizin is even a harsher word, it sort of means
like like splatter. Anyway, in front of it. Okay. And that's that's
how you worship it. אמרה amra so she said, מוטב שתחזור היא
אשה לחולה mutav shetachazor hi isha l'chola better I should go back
to being sick and you know I should go back to die
from my sickness, ולא תעבוד עבודה זרה בכך v'lo taavod avoda zara
b'kach I shall not worship a god in this disgusting fashion. Okay,
so that's what even she drew her line at the worship of
פעור. Peor. That was this non-Jewish woman. ואתם בית ישראל אינם כן
v'atem beit Yisrael einam kein you, the Jewish people, when you decided
to worship עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you were not like that. הנצמדים
לבעל פעור hanitzmadim l'Baal Peor it says that you cleaved to בעל
פעור. Baal Peor. What does it mean you cleaved? כצמיד פתיל, k'tzamid
patil, a צמיד פתיל tzamid patil is like a is like a
seal on a jar that's like vacuum packed, you know, like totally
sealed, like totally like you know totally glued on. Okay, so when
you were ran after the בעל פעור, Baal Peor, nobody could separate
you from it. So you know, so just to show how how
we are you know how extreme we were when we followed our
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay. And that in contrast to how you
felt about God. Even when you were feeling about God, you know,
positively. ואתם הדבקים בהשם אלקיכם v'atem hadveikim b'Hashem Elokeichem you who stick
to השם Hashem your God, חיים כולכם היום chayim kulchem hayom so
that's just sticking. That's not cleaving. כשתי תמרות הדבוקות זו בזו k'shtei
tmarot hadvukot zo b'zo like two dates that are like stuck to
one another, it's very easy to pull them apart. Okay. It's not
like a like a waxed on seal. Okay, so your עבודה זרה
avoda zara you you were much more passionate about than you were
about ever about God. Pretty big condemnation. במתניתא תנא b'matnita tana a
ברייתא braita we read it in a in a softer way. הנצמדים
לבעל פעור hanitzmadim l'Baal Peor נצמדים nitzmadim we don't mean like to
cleave like with this like tight seal, but we read it כצמיד
על ידי אשה k'tzamid al yedei isha like a bracelet on a
woman. You know, so a bracelet isn't so tight, right? It's like
dangling, there's a lot of air. So even when we went after
בעל פעור Baal Peor we were not so you know so adhering
adhering whatever it's not so cleaving. ואתם הדבקים בהשם אלקיכם v'atem hadveikim
b'Hashem Elokeichem דבוקים ממש dvukim mamash but you who stick to God,
ah, with God you really stick stick with God. Okay, so that's
the opposite, that our connection to God was stronger than our connection
to בעל פעור. Baal Peor. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan here's another story
of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. מעשה בסבתא בן אלס maaseh b'Savta ben
Alas this person סבתא בן אלס Savta ben Alas or some say
מן אלס min Alas from this city of אלס, Alas, okay, שהשכיר
חמורו לנכרית אחת she'hiskir chamoro l'nochrit achat this was a Jew and
he rented out his donkey to a non-Jewish woman. He was a
donkey driver. כיוון שהגיע לפעור keivan shehigia l'Peor so he was taking
her on some trip, they came to a פעור Peor temple. אמרה
לו amra lo she said to him, המתן עד שאכנס ואצא hamten
ad she'ekaneis v'atzeh you know what, stay take a stop here, I
want to go in and pay my worship. Do my worship. Let
me go in and come out. לאחר שיצאה le'achar sheyatzah she came
out, אמר לה amar lah אף את המתיני לי עד שאכנס ואצא
af at hamtini li ad she'ekaneis v'atzeh you know what, can you
stay by the donkey? I also want to go in and do
my worship. All right, this was a and he wasn't being a
mocking, he was serious. This was a Jew who worshipped the פעור.
Peor. אמרה לו amra lo she said to him, ולא יהודי אתה
v'lo Yehudi atah aren't you a Jew? So אמר לה amar lah
ומה איכפת לך u'mah ichpat lach what do you care? Fine, I'm
a Jew but I like the worship of פעור. Peor. נכנס nichnas
he went in, פער בפניו paar b'fanav he defecated in front of
it, וקינח בחוטמו v'kinach b'chotmo and he wiped himself with the nose
of the idol. Okay. והיו משרתי עבודה זרה מקלסין לו v'hayu mshartei
avoda zara m'kalsin lo and the attendants were praising him, ואומרין v'omrin
מעולם לא היה אדם שעבדו לזו בכך me'olam lo hayah adam she'avdo
l'zo b'kach nobody ever worshipped our god this in this wonderful way.
You really understand that the way to worship our god is to
completely disgrace it or something. Okay, so anyway just again that was
ending the whole thing by I think another mockery of of the
gods, which was keeping in that theme. So very interesting themes here
of the intertwining of יצר הרע דעבודה זרה yetzer hara d'avoda zara
and יצר הרע yetzer hara of sexuality, and how we you know
have inter at times internalized it and so ran after it, and
then ends with a little bit of a of a mockery. Okay.
Now going back to halachic discussions. הפוער עצמו לבעל פעור הרי זו
עבודתו hapoer atzmo l'Baal Peor harei zo avodato so this is ultimately
if somebody defecates in front of בעל פעור, Baal Peor, that's the
way it's worshipped and that's עבודה זרה. avoda zara. אף על גב
דמכוין לבזויה af al gav d'michavein l'vazuya even though you're trying to
do something like this previous story to base I don't know if
he was trying to do it but even if somebody's trying to
do it as a way of sort of degrading it, you know
showing it's you know doing a a shaming act or something or
a degrading act, it's still an act of עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
I want to get I'll get back to that in a minute,
but let's finish the משנה. mishna. Doesn't matter what your intent was.
הזורק אבן למרקוליס הרי זו עבודתו, Hazorek even le-Markulis harei zu avodato,
if you throw a stone to מרקוליס, Markulis, that's an act of
worship. אף על גב דמכוין למירגמי, Af al gav de-michavein le-mirgemei, even
if in your mind you think what you're doing is you're throwing
stones not to it, but at it. You're actually trying to stone
it. It doesn't matter. You did the עבודה avoda and you've done
the act. רב מנשיא הוי קאזיל לבי תורתא. Rav Menashya hava ka-azil
le-bei Tortah. So רב מנשיא Rav Menashya was going to this place,
לבי תורתא. Bei Tortah. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, people said to him,
עבודה זרה היא, Avoda zara hi, you know that place there, that
thing there in that place, that's an idol. דקאי הכא, De-kaei hacha,
that's standing there in that place that you're going. So, oh, he
said, that's an idol? שקל פתא שדא בה. Shakal patta shada bah.
He took a piece, a clump of earth and he threw it
at the idol as a way of, of you know, of showing
disrespect. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, then they said to him, wait wait,
מרקוליס היא. Markulis hi. Oh, did we forget to tell you? It's
actually מרקוליס. Markulis. So אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them,
so you just now did an act of עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
you gotta do תשובה. teshuva. So he said no, אמר להן, Amar
lehen, he said to them, where was he? אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, הזורק אבן למרקוליס תנן. Hazorek even le-Markulis tenan.
It says if you throw stone to מרקוליס, Markulis, it's an act
of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. I didn't throw it to it, I
threw it at it, okay? אזלו שאלו בי מדרשא, Azalu sha'alu bei
midrasha, they went and they asked in the בית מדרש. beit midrash.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, הזורק אבן במרקוליס תנן,
Hazorek even be-Markulis tenan, which is not our משנה, Mishna, but anyway.
They said no no no, it's even if you throw it at
it, that's an act of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. אף על גב
דמכוין למירגמי, Af al gav de-michavein le-mirgemei, even if you're trying to
stone it, it's still an act of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, איזיל ואשקליה? Eizil ve-eshkalyei? So he said, okay, so
fine, I did the עבירה, aveira, I'll do תשובה. teshuva. Should I
try now to go ahead and like remove the stone so it
shouldn't remain there as a, you know, that my stone is there
as an offering to the עבודה זרה? avoda zara? Meaning I'm not
gonna that won't change the sin that I did, but let me
at least go ahead and remove it. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they
said to him, אחד הנוטלה ואחד הנותנה חייב. Echad ha-notlah ve-echad ha-notnah
chayav. An act of worship is both the placing of a stone
and the removing of a stone is also an act of worship.
Why? חדא וחדא רווחא לחבריה שביק. Chada ve-chada revacha le-chavereih shevik. When
you remove a stone, you're allowing the next person to put a
stone in that place. So part of the act of worship is
after you throw it, actually removing it is also an act of
worship. So, you know, it's like the guy who, you know, you
walk into the room and you're not thinking, you turn on the
light on שבת. Shabbat. Oh, I forgot it's שבת, Shabbat, and then
you turn it off. So that actually makes it worse, okay? You
just don't do it twice. Alright, anyway. So this is a very
important question, this last thing, because we've discussed earlier, if you remember,
אביי ורבא, Abaye ve-Rava, if somebody does an act of worship from
אהבה ויראה. ahava ve-yira. And you know, certainly according to רבא, Rava,
it seems like it's only an act of worship if you are
doing it because you believe in this god. So if, and you
know, so according to אביי, Abaye, so according to רבא, Rava, why
if you are throwing a stone at an idol, like is it
in a way of disrespect or defecating in a way of disrespect,
why is it an act of עבודה זרה? avoda zara? That's not
an act of worship, okay? So that is a big question the
ראשונים Rishonim have to deal with. So תוספות Tosafot says, so some
say that this only means you would never be put to death
for this. You'd only be put to death if it was done
as an intentional act of worship, okay? But this is that you
are like you would bring like a קרבן, korban, like it would
be in sin בשוגג. be-shogeg. So in that case, even though the
intent was missing, since it was the same the act of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, even though your intent was different, you would still
bring a קרבן. korban. קרבן Korban is all sin when you do
the act with a different intent, although you could say here the
intent totally changes the act. Anyway, that's one answer. Another answer which
תוספות Tosafot says is תוספות Tosafot says no. Again, it doesn't explain
this case here where the rabbi did it by accident, but תוספות
Tosafot basically says even when the גמרא Gemara says that if you
do it you're חייב chayav when you do it as a way
of disrespect, that's a way of disrespect but you still believe in
the god. Meaning it's not like you don't believe in the god,
right? There's a disrespect like this is all nonsense and I'm gonna
show how much it's nonsense, I'm gonna go defecate on it, right?
Or you could say no no no, I believe in this god
but I'm angry let's say with the god, or I'm gonna do
this act of worship but I'm gonna do it in a disrespectful
way, right? Like you know, like somebody says fine, you want to
see me take לולב, lulav, here then I'll take לולב, lulav, you
know? So you can take it in a disrespectful way and it
still be understood in the context of believing in the god and
worshipping the god. That's the way תוספות Tosafot understands. And then a
number of commentators on the רמב"ם Rambam understand a third way, which
is the following, which is and this is very important. I'm not
I mean I don't know the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't say this, but
some introduced this distinction I'm about to say to deal with this
problem: that it matters whether this is a god that already is
worshipped in this way or whether you're doing something new. Meaning the
גמרא Gemara before, or making a new god. The גמרא Gemara before,
this is a significant limiting of the idea of אהבה ויראה, ahava
ve-yira, this approach. It says the גמרא Gemara before that said that
somebody who worships a god מאהבה ומיראה me-ahava u-me-yira has not transgressed,
that's when no this says nobody's worshipping this thing. You all of
a sudden decided this thing is gonna be my god and then
you go ahead and like worship it מאהבה ומיראה me-ahava u-me-yira or
whatever, that's when you're לא חייב lo chayav until you you really
accept it as your god. That's talking when you're making a new...
something out of nothing. Then you really have to accept it as
your god. But a god that already has an established following and
people worship it and it has rituals, in that type of a
case, if you go through the act even if you don't believe
in it, and even if you're doing the act with a different
intent, it's still an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so
that's a significant limiting of that previous discussion. That says all that
discussion that you need belief for it to be עבודה זרה avodah
zarah was when the nobody else looked at it as an עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. But something that is accepted by a follow people
by followers
as a god, your belief doesn't matter. And if you do the
act, that's an act עבודה זרה avodah zarah even if you're doing
it like this way, in a degrading and disrespectful way. Okay, so
it's a very all these big, big questions are still left a
little bit hanging in the air. All right, now we move on
to the next משנה, mishna, yes.
Would there even be a concept of doing some kind of act
of worship out of אהבה ahavah and יראה yirah if it's not
anybody else's god?
Yeah, so that's why it work this answer works better for Rambam,
because you'll remember that Rambam said אהבה ahavah and יראה yirah was
not אהבה ahavah and יראה yirah of a person. He said that
אהבה ahavah and יראה yirah was that you are like you you
love the way this image looks or you all of a sudden
have the decided that you're afraid of what might happen to you,
so it's more your own like, you know sort of quasi-religious motivation
and it's not somebody else's or the case of Haman was a
case of אהבה ahavah and יראה yirah of a person, but it
was somebody's creating a new god. Haman said I'm god and worship
me. So that would be the cases of אהבה ahavah and יראה
yirah when you're either you or somebody else is creating a new
god and you're being pressured to worship it. But an established religion
that's got a following, then as long as you do the same
act, you understand the idea, once it's an established religion and these
acts are interpreted in a certain way, right, who cares what's going
on in your head, you know? So you understand the logic behind
that. But yeah, you you'd have to make explain the circumstances in
a particular way. Okay. המוסר מזרעו למולך, Hamoseir mizaro lamolech, now how
this is I identified out as separate from עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and we'll see why. Somebody who gives over his seed, his children
to the Molech. אינו חייב עד שימסור למולך, Eino chayav ad sheyimsor
lamolech, you have to be give it over. It says כי מזרעו
נתן למולך, ki mizaro natan lamolech, anyway you have to give it
over to the priests. And then it says, you know, להעביר למולך.
leha'avir lamolech. So you have to give the son the child has
to be given over, and then it has to be passed through
the fire, both needs to be done. אינו חייב עד שימסור למולך
ויעביר באש Eino chayav ad sheyimsor lamolech veya'avir ba'eish and is passed
through the fire. We'll see whether the father was involved, I guess
it could be the mother too, anyway involved in passing the child
through the fire. מסר למולך ולא העביר באש, Masar lamolech velo he'evir
ba'eish, it was handed over but it wasn't pass the child wasn't
passed through. העביר באש ולא מסר למולך, He'evir ba'eish velo masar lamolech,
or passed through and not handed over. אינו חייב עד שימסור למולך
ויעביר באש. Eino chayav ad sheyimsor lamolech veya'avir ba'eish. No, sorry, you
don't you don't get the death penalty until you do both. Okay.
קתני עבודה זרה וקתני מולך. Katani avodah zarah vekatani molech. Now first
we discussed עבודה זרה avodah zarah was one of those that gets
סקילה sekilah and then we said Molech is one of those that
gets סקילה. sekilah. Sounds like it's not just a form of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, sounds like it's something distinct. אמר רבי אבין תני
כמאן דאמר מולך לאו עבודה זרה היא. Amar Rabi Avin tani keman
de'amar molech lav avodah zarah hi. Okay, it's not an עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. It is some pagan ritual but not the worship of
a god. Okay. You can understand that, right? I mean you can
have rituals that are not, especially if they think that maybe it's
acting with some metaphysical forces, you know, and on some metaphysical forces.
I mean whenever we hear children and fire whatever we obviously think
that it's a type of child child sacrifice to a god, but
there's one opinion that says no, it is a pagan ritual but
not a worship of a god. All right, and it's חייב סקילה.
chayav sekilah. Now, you would say why would you get סקילה sekilah
if it's not עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? But you know one of
the places where the Torah talks about Molech, it says לא ימצא
בך מעביר בנו ובתו באש, lo yimatzei becha ma'avir bno uvito ba'eish,
let's not be found you anybody who passes their children into a
fire, קוסם קסמים מעונן ומנחש ומכשף, kosem ksamim me'onein umnacheish umchashef, and
then it says witchcraft and necromancy and all these other things. So
actually the Molech prohibition appears in a context not just of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah but a context of all these other types of
black magic type things. So that's the question: is it עבודה זרה
avodah zarah or is it more like witchcraft? Okay, so in this
answer it's more like witchcraft. Okay.
דתניא, Detanya, now this is this a debate, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, אחד המולך ואחד שאר עבודה זרה חייב. echad hamolech ve'echad
shear avodah zarah chayav. Whether you do this worship to this fire
thing to the Molech or to any עבודה זרה avodah zarah you're
חייב. chayav. רבי אליעזר בר רבי שמעון אומר למולך חייב שלא למולך
פטור. Rabi Eliezer be-Rabi Shimon omer lamolech chayav shelo lamolech patur. For
Molech you're חייב, chayav, for other things you're not. Now what does
that have to do with whether it's an עבודה זרה avodah zarah
an act of עבודה זרה avodah zarah or not? Whether it's limited
to the Molech. So the assumption here is, it's not in immediately
obvious, but here's the assumption. If it is an act of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, so why would the Torah have to tell me
not to do it? The Torah already tells me not to do
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So this is just like every other act
of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Now of course obviously it's very present
in the Torah because clearly it was a very dominant act of,
you know, that was, you know, it was a big יצר הרע
yeitzer hara to that, like it seemed very much that that was
something that people were straying after, maybe because it was particularly horrific.
But from a legal perspective we're saying if the Torah already said
don't worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. מולך? Molech? So this is just
like every other act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Now of course
obviously it's very present in the תורה Torah because clearly it was
a very dominant act that was a big יצר הרע yetzer hara
to that. Like it seemed very much that that was something that
people were straying after, maybe because it was particularly horrific. But from
a legal perspective we're saying if the תורה Torah already said don't
worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, why would it have to say don't
worship מולך Molech if it's also an עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? And
the answer is ah, must be you're חייב, chayav, the תורה's Torah
telling you you're חייב chayav for the worship of מולך Molech even
when it's not the normal way it's worshiped. Okay, or else it
wouldn't have to single it out. So if it's going to tell
me you're חייב chayav even if it's not the normal way you're
worship, it wouldn't just be limited to מולך, Molech, it would be
any time I did this act to any god, even if it's
not the way that god is normally worshiped, I'd be חייב. chayav.
So if you think מולך Molech is עבודה זרה avodah zarah based
on the rabbinic sort of logic of the economy of פסוקים, pesukim,
it leads to the conclusion that עבודה זרה avodah zarah that you're
חייב chayav if you do it to any god. But if you
think that מולך Molech is not an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, then
it's just this one particular ritual, a ritual done to the מולך,
Molech, it's not an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the תורה Torah is
telling it to you because even though it's not an עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it's a pagan ritual and you're חייב chayav for it.
Okay, so you got, the one that says it applies to other
gods says it's an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The one that says
it applies only to מולך, Molech, whatever מולך Molech means if it's
not a god, but anyway it says that that's a ritual but
not an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So let's read that again. דתניא
אחד למולך ואחד לשאר עבודה זרה חייב. De-tanya echad la-Molech ve-echad li-shear
avodah zarah chayav. That assumes it is an עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and it applies to any god. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר למולך
חייב שלא למולך פטור. Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon omer la-Molech chayav she-lo
la-Molech patur. No, only to מולך, Molech, which is being read here
to mean it's not an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it's only a
ritual and only done in this way. אמר אביי רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון ורבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אמרו דבר אחד. Amar Abaye Rabbi Elazar
be-Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos amru davar echad. They said the
same position. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון הדאמר, Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon had-amar,
that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon we just said,
that only to the מולך Molech and it's a ritual, it's not
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס דתניא רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס אומר מפני מה תפסה תורה לשון מולך. Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos
de-tanya Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer mipnei mah tafsah Torah lashon Molech.
What is the meaning of the word מולך? Molech? Obviously it suggests
a word like מלך, melech, king. So כל שהיא ממליכו עליהם אפילו
צרור ואפילו קיסם. Kol she-hi mamlicho aleihem afilu tzeror va-afilu kisam. Even
if they just took a little rock and a little twig, a
little, you know, and they said "this is the מולך Molech and
we're now going to do the ritual," that would be the ritual.
So we're assuming that I can't mean that that's an עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Maybe that's a thing to give you your components of
the ritual but they say ah, you see, this is consistent with
the idea that it's not really an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
the גמרא Gemara says רבא אמר מולך הרי איכא בינייהו. Rava amar
Molech harei ika beiniyahu. No, they're not saying the exact same thing.
According to the second opinion, even if you just ad hoc designated
something as מולך, Molech, then it's then that's the act, whereas according
to the other position it might not be an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah but it has to be something that has been like has
a permanent designation of מולך. Molech. You wouldn't agree to this ad
hoc idea. Okay.
So כל שהיא ממליכו עליהם kol she-hi mamlicho aleihem and then questions
on it, אפילו צרור אפילו קיסם? afilu tzeror afilu kisam?
No, not question. That's, no,
declarative, it's not a question. אפילו צרור ואפילו קיסם. Afilu tzeror va-afilu
kisam. Okay, so anyway, so if it's a ritual, it's something is
called מולך, Molech, even an ad hoc thing or a regular thing,
but it's not an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And that's one approach,
as opposed to being an act done to one of, to any
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rabbi Yannai, said רבי
ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, אינו חייב עד שימסרנו למשרתי עבודה זרה. Eino chayav
ad she-yimsarenu le-meshartai avodah zarah.
Now we're going back and essentially saying what was in the משנה.
Mishnah. You have to give it over to the attendants. He's assuming
it is an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You have to give it
over to the attendants. It, the son, excuse me, you're going to
have to give your child over to the attendants. שנאמר ומזרעך לא
תתן להעביר למולך. She-neemar u-mi-zaracha lo titten le-haavir la-Molech.
Don't give it over, לא תתן. lo titten. Okay, we're basically just
explicating our משנה. Mishnah. תניא נמי הכי ונתת לו יכול העביר ולא
מסר יהא חייב. Tanya nami hachi ve-natata lo yachol he-evir ve-lo masar
yehei chayav. Maybe just giving over with, maybe passing through the fire
without giving the kid over, you're חייב. chayav. תלמוד לומר לא תתן.
Talmud lomar lo titten.
Don't give. So part of the transgression is the giving over to
the priest. מסר למולך ולא העביר יכול יהא חייב. Masar la-Molech ve-lo
he-evir yachol yehei chayav. Maybe if you gave your child to the
priest but they didn't pass him through the fire, maybe you're חייב.
chayav.
תלמוד לומר להעביר. Talmud lomar le-haavir.
To pass through. Now you could mean, you could read it it
means you gave it to the priest for the purpose of passing
the kid through but they didn't actually pass this kid through, but
that's not how we're reading it. We're reading להעביר le-haavir means giving
the kid to the priest and they actually then went ahead and
passed the kid through. So you need both components. מסר והעביר שלא
למולך יכול יהא
חייב. Masar ve-he-evir she-lo la-Molech yachol yehei chayav. Back to this question
does it apply to other things that aren't מולך? Molech? Maybe you're
חייב chayav without doing it for the מולך. Molech. תלמוד לומר למולך.
Talmud lomar la-Molech. No, it only when it's לא תתן להעביר למולך.
lo titten le-haavir la-Molech. Each word is being read. Given over to
the priest, passed through the fire to the מולך. Molech. מסר והעביר
למולך ובלא אש יכול יהא חייב. Masar ve-he-evir la-Molech u-ve-lo esh yachol
yehei chayav. Maybe if you did the whole thing but you didn't
do the fire ritual. By the way, it's not clear and we're
going to see, did the child, was the kid burned? Before we
read a פסוק pasuk that said they burn their kids. Here it's
going to seem very much that the גמרא Gemara understands that there
was some ritual that was passed between fires or over a fire,
but actually the kid was not killed, maybe not even injured. Okay,
but there was still this ritual. So יכול יהא חייב. yachol yehei
chayav. Now, maybe if you did it without a fire, יכול יהא
חייב, yachol yehei chayav, maybe you transgressed. נאמר כאן להעביר, Neemar kan
le-haavir, so one verse says לא תתן להעביר למולך, lo titten le-haavir
la-Molech, it doesn't mention fire. ונאמר להלן, Ve-neemar le-hallan, another verse says,
or the verse I quoted to you before, לא ימצא בך מעביר
בנו ובתו באש, Lo yimatze becha maavir bno u-vito ba-esh, don't pass
your kids through a fire. So presumably we're talking about the same
ritual. the passing your children. So מה להלן באש, mah le'hallan ba'esh,
the same way there it's a fire, אף כאן באש, af kan
ba'esh, here too when it speaks about the מולך molech it means
a fire. ומה כאן מולך, u'mah kan molech, now the same way
the verse says מולך, molech, אף להלן, af le'hallan, there when it
speaks about the fire, it doesn't say מולך molech but it means
מולך. molech. So we basically put the פסוקים pesukim together, which makes
a lot of sense, this fire ritual to the מולך. molech. אמר
רב אחא בריה דרבא, amar Rav Acha brei d'Rava, העביר כל זרעו
פטור. he'evir kol zaro patur. If a person
had all of his kids go through the ritual, he's exempt, שנאמר,
she'ne'emar,
מזרעך mi'zaracha ולא כל זרעך, v'lo kol zaracha, from your kids, not
all your kids. Now תוספות Tosafot says, I don't understand, you did
one kid you're חייב, chayav, you do the next kid now you
get off for the first kid? So תוספות Tosafot says no, either
it means somebody only has one child, so the one kid is
all your kids, or you did all your kids at the same
time. But תוספות Tosafot says if you did one kid and were
חייב, chayav, you wouldn't then go ahead and tomorrow do the next
kid and retroactively be פטור patur from what you did the day
before. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says it means you did all of
your kids at one time. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, now
רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, העבירו סומא
מהו, he'eviro suma mahu, ישן מהו? yashen mahu? So let's say the
kid was blind or asleep, like he wasn't aware fully of what
was happening. I blind you were aware, but you weren't seeing. Anyway,
would that be considered having the kid go through the fire? בן
בנו בת בתו מהו, ben b'no bat bito mahu, let's say it
was a grandkid. Okay, תפשוט מחדא, tifshot michada, so one of those
we can answer. דתניא, d'tanya, כי מזרעו נתן למולך, ki mi'zaro natan
la'molech, he gave from his seed to the מולך. molech. מה תלמוד
לומר, mah talmud lomar, why does it say זרעו? zaro? לפי שנאמר,
lefi she'ne'emar, לא ימצא בך מעביר בנו ובתו באש, lo yimatzei becha
ma'avir b'no u'vito ba'esh, son or daughter. אין לי אלא בנו ובתו,
ein li ella b'no u'vito, I only know son or daughter. בן
בנו ובת בתו מניין, ben b'no u'vat bito minayin, how do I
know grandkid? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, בתתו מזרעו למולך. b'tito mi'zaro la'molech.
So that at least answers, we don't know the blind or the
asleep question. By the way, you know they probably were certainly for
child sacrifice, probably you know they used to like drug the kids
or whatever so they wouldn't you know be able to go along
with it. But anyway, so we don't know the answer to that
question, but it doesn't have to be kid, direct child, it could
be grandkid as well. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara just has a
question. תנא פתח בכי מזרעו, tana petach b'ki mi'zaro, it started quoting
the verse כי מזרעו נתן למולך, ki mi'zaro natan la'molech, which is
seed and not son or daughter, any descendant. וסיים בבתתו מזרעו, v'siyam
b'tito mi'zaro, but then it quotes another פסוק pasuk about seed. It
says when he gave from his seed. So which of the פסוקים
pesukim are we דרשן-ing, darshan מזרעו נתן mi'zaro natan or בבתתו מזרעו?
b'tito mi'zaro? I mean they're essentially saying the same thing, but which
one are we focusing on? So the גמרא Gemara says, you know
what, דרשה אחריני היא, drasha achrinei hi, you're right. That extra phrase
בבתתו מזרעו b'tito mi'zaro is telling you a different דרשה. drasha. מזרעו
נתן למולך mi'zaro natan la'molech says it doesn't have to be son
or daughter, it could be grandkid because it says זרע. zera. ובבתתו
מזרעו למולך u'v'tito mi'zaro la'molech is telling you yet another point. זרעו,
zaro, his seed. אין לי אלא זרע כשר, ein li ella zera
kasher, I only know a kosher child, meaning like not a ממזר.
mamzer. זרע פסול מניין, zera pasul minayin, how do I know even
for example if it was like a ממזר mamzer or something of
that nature? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, בבתתו מזרעו. b'tito mi'zaro. Okay, when
he gave over from his seed, so the extra מזרעו mi'zaro maybe
means from even a partial aspect, even a not the whatever, anyway
somehow includes even a ממזר. mamzer. Let's just read one more line
about this to discuss the actual ritual. אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, אינו חייב עד שיעבירנו דרך העברה. eino chayav ad she'ya'avirenu derech
ha'avara. You have to do it a normal way in which they
would pass the kids through the fire. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what
does that mean? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, שרגא דלבני מבינציא. sharga d'livnei
mi'beinitzia. You'd have a row of bricks going down the middle, he'd
walk on a row of bricks, נורא מהאי גיסא ונורא מהאי גיסא,
nura me'hai gissa v'nura me'hai gissa, fire on this side, fire on
that side. So he wouldn't be thrown in the fire, he would
walk between the fires on this row of bricks. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, כמשוורתא דפוריא, k'mashvarta d'puraya, like when they jump on פורים. Purim.
Basically you would jump over a fire pit. תניא כוותיה דרבא, tanya
k'vatei d'Rava, we taught like רבא, Rava, אינו חייב עד שיעבירנו דרך
העברה, eino chayav ad she'ya'avirenu derech ha'avara, it has to be the
normal way that they would pass through the fire. העבירו ברגל פטור,
he'eviro b'regel patur, if you just walked through you're פטור, patur, so
it means it's not about walking, so presumably it's about jumping. ואינו
חייב אלא על יוצאי יריכו. v'eino chayav ella al yotzei yericho. Anyway,
so one is, so that seems to support רבא, Rava, it's like
jumping over a fire pit, not walking between fires. And now, since
we mentioned it doesn't have to be son or daughter, it could
be a descendant, descendant fine, but it can't be a relative in
some other direction, going up or to the side, it has to
only go down. הכיצד, ha'keitzad, בנו ובתו חייב, b'no u'vito chayav, son
or daughter you're חייב, chayav, and even a grandkid as we mentioned
before. אביו ואמו, aviv v'imo, father or mother, אחיו ואחותו, achiv v'achoto,
brother or sister, פטור, patur, you're exempt. העביר עצמו פטור, he'evir atzmo
patur, let's say you put yourself through the fire, you're also exempt.
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון מחייב, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon mechayiv, רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says you're חייב chayav if you
did yourself. אחד למולך ואחד לשאר עבודה זרה חייב, echad la'molech v'echad
l'shear avoda zara chayav, and then the other point we said, whether
it's מולך molech or to another idol. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
למולך חייב שלא למולך פטור, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer la'molech chayav
she'lo la'molech patur, only to the מולך, molech, that's what we quoted
at the beginning. So let's just read one more. So אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, מה טעמא דרבי אליעזר בר שמעון? mah taama de-Rabbi Eliezer
bar Shimon? Why does רבי אליעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Eliezer bar Shimon
say even if you pass yourself to the מולך Molech you're חייב?
chayav? אמר קרא Amar kra the verse says, לא ימצא בך מעביר
בנו ובתו באש. Lo yimatze becha maavir bino u-vito ba-esh. Don't let
it be found in you. You can't do it even to yourself.
He's reading the בך becha to say don't even do it to
yourself. בך בעצמך becha be-atzmecha don't even do it to yourself. So
the Gemara says רבנן לא דרשי בך? Rabbanan lo darshei becha? Wait
a minute. So why did the Rabbis argue? The Rabbis normally agree
that that's how we read the word בך. becha. והתנן ve-hatnan the
Mishnah says, אבדתו ואבדת אביו שלו קודמת. Avedato ve-avedat aviv shelo kodemet.
If you have to decide between returning your lost object to yourself
or lost object to your father, you come first. It's a general
principle, right? You have to take care of your own interests before
somebody else's. So where do we know that from? ואמרינן מאי טעמא?
ve-amrinan mai taama? What's the reason? ואמר רב יהודה אמר קרא, Ve-amar
Rav Yehuda amar kra, אפס כי לא יהיה בך אביון. Efes ki
lo yihyeh becha evyon. There shall not be a poor person among
you. Where we read it as לא יהיה בך אביון. lo yihyeh
becha evyon. You can't let yourself become poor. Okay? שלו קודמת לשל
כל אדם. shelo kodemet le-shel kol adam. So do you see we
read בך becha means don't do it to yourself? So if we
say that by the lost object, why do we disagree when it
comes to the מולך? Molech? So the Gemara says התם מאפס. hatam
me-Efes. No, no, no. The point isn't just the word בך. becha.
It's the word אפס. Efes. Rashi says the word אפס Efes means
אפס afeis to get rid of. אפס afeis get rid of poverty.
And the way you can get rid of poverty, you do have
to start with making sure that you're not poor. So it's not
just the word of בך. becha. It's the word of בך becha
together with the word אפס Efes says you gotta take care of
your own interests first. Okay, but the בך becha itself, רבי אליעזר
בר שמעון Rabbi Eliezer bar Shimon says it means don't do this
ritual to yourself, but the Rabbis say no, no, no, it's only
when you do it to your kid, not when you do it
to yourself. Okay, we will wrap up. I know we only have
a few lines left, but we're already a little over, so we
will wrap this up tomorrow.